This task is about modeling with state charts.
And yeah, we've been given a text task which
we have to read and then understand and
then we have to create a state chart.
For its next invention Gyro Gearloose
needs a device which allows to input
numbers consisting of three digits from one
to four. Gyro envisages the device as follows.
The device has a screen with three digits on it.
At each moment exactly one of the three digits is
active. At the beginning, all three digits are
equal to one, and the leftmost digit is active.
Additionally, the device has five buttons.
Plus, minus, L, R, and OK. When plus or minus
is pressed, the active digit is incremented,
respectively decremented by one.
If the digit would become higher than four
or lower than one by this, then it becomes
one respectively four.
The buttons L
and R have structurally different functions.
Pressing R activates the digit to the right
of the current active one. If the rightmost
digit is already active before pressing of R,
then instead the leftmost digit becomes active.
Pressing L on the other hand will
always switch to the leftmost digit.
If that one is not already active anyway.
When okay is pressed, the input process ends.
And now we have to help Gyro by giving a UML
state diagram, modeling the descriptive device
and we have to use hierarchical states
and possibly regions in order to keep
the size of the model reasonably small.
And here is a picture of the device. So,
we have three digits going up to four, and we
have plus, minus button buttons, L R and OK.
So, I guess we should start by having some states.
At least, we require these four number states
for each digit. So, maybe let's just start by
having those states here as numbers. So, 1, 2, 3
and 4. These are just states for the numbers.
So, these we require anyway, probably for all
of the digits. But let's just start with the
obvious things. So, we have plus and minus, which
shall change the state. When we press plus, we
increment the number. So, that's this direction.
And when we are already at
the highest number-. Maybe
let's draw this from here. When we
are already at the highest number,
then we go back to the first. So,
let me choose a plus here as design for
incrementing the numbers and then we have the
other direction as well. So, we can go from four
to three by decrementing using the minus button.
And again from, when we reach one, and
we press minus, we end up in four again.
Okay, so this was the easy
part of this functionality.
So, this is just for one digit, okay? And
we have somehow to repeat the whole process.
So, let me make this a bit more dense and
add the labels inside here. So, basically that's what
the switching of the numbers does, and
we have this whole thing three times,
and we have one number which is active, and
then we have two numbers, which are inactive.
And this could lead to the thought that we can use
actually history in order to store the values. So,
we could keep track of the other
numbers using history. And therefore,
we would require for each digit a history point
as well. So, I will add a history node here. And
that's the basic part which I have in
mind for yeah, using or reusing this part.
So, I will create a state around this, which
basically contains the whole part here.
So, this shall be a basic state that we can now
repeat three times so that we have three digits.
And yeah, we can of course, label them. I
haven't added a label yet. So, one is digit
one and then we have digit two and three as well
and the digit three. These are the parts. And
yeah, we can switch from each part to another part
by going there using the history
node. So, we can switch from the
first part, from the first digit to the second
using the history when we use the R button. So,
when we are in this state, we can use
the R button and then we will switch
to the second number and then we can use the
R button and it will be at the third number.
And we can check the text again. It activates
the digit to the right, this R button. And
if the rightmost button is active, then
we use our in order to go to the leftmost
button. Okay. So, maybe I moved this label over
here so that I can draw labels here.
Okay, so maybe let's go from here.
We can go from digit two to digit
three, we can go from digit one to digit two.
Maybe I move the whole part a bit. So,
that we have a bit more space in between.
Okay. So, and when we are in digit
three, then we can go back to digit one
and this should be the history
node that we reach then.
So, this is the R button. So, let's create
labels for these, this is the R button
and then we have the L button as well, which
always leads to the leftmost digit. So,
we can skip it for the first digit actually,
because when we are at first digit,
we are not required to go to the leftmost digit
because we are already there. So, there is no such
required. If we are in the right most we simply
reuse this one here. So, we use L in this case
and then we have digit two when we want press L
there then we actually-, when we are here, then
we can go up there. Okay. So, this is
L in this case. It's quite tight here.
Maybe I should move these arrows a bit out so
that we can see it properly. So, these are
different. So, this is for L and this is for
R and L. So, this makes it maybe much clearer.
Move this up here. So, and okay, this is what
remembering the state's just as histories,
but we need to provide more information and that
is especially how the whole action starts. And
I will make some more space here.
Yeah, we need another state around the
whole thing which is the complete device.
So, I create a new state and this should be the
device and I want to place this whole thing into
and because state is maybe, like this.
So, this is the complete state around it. And
now we can think about how to enter the state.
So, the device has a screen with three digits,
that's was what it says, and we have
at the beginning: all three
digits are equal to one.
So, and we start with the leftmost digit, and
we can represent this so we have a start state.
Let's start with the outermost starting state,
which simply goes to our device here. So, we go
from here to our outer state, which represents the
device. And then we have a starting state inside,
which is the first number, because this
is where we are going to start by selecting.
So, that's our inner starting state. And
then we start at one. So, this is another
starting state. So, we start at one. Okay.
Then we have the history,
which when we leave the state, we can
either go to digit two, or digit three.
And they are all starting at one. That is why
we require an arrow from our history to one.
So, that means when we switch the digit
using R or L, well, L don’t make sense,
digit one. But when we switch to the right,
using R, we are in our first in state one. And
then if you switch to two, and use R, then we
start here in one as well. And when we switch
to two here, and then switch using or L
back to digit one, and then go to R again,
then we have the history remember
our old state, and we'll be there again.
So, that means we keep track of our history.
And thus, we keep the state and as we have
the starting state in digit one, and we start in
digit one, how we can just keep our history node
around. So, this is flat history here, because
it's enough, we just require the history to
keep the state at that level. So, remember,
a digit from one state from one to four, for our
digits. And, yeah, you have the starting state
here, and there's just one thing left. And
that is ending the whole thing.
And the task says for the ending,
that we can have a OK button. And when
we press OK, the input process ends.
So, you have an end state here. And whenever we
are ready, we can you can use this state here.
Okay. And there is the label missing. So, this
is the OK button. And now, let's check back to
our picture, we have the plus buttons represented
here in our digits, we have the minus buttons in
which go the opposite direction decrementing
the numbers and we have our L and R. L going
always to the leftmost state, but when we are
in digit one, we don't have to change anything.
And the R button which goes from digit one to
digit two, and from digit two to digit three,
and from digit three to digit one. And we have the
OK button, which ends the whole process. And so,
I just realized it wasn't in view
here below so plus minus, L, R and OK.
So, we are done with our state
diagram and solve this task as well.